BU Records: Spanish Department, Inclusive: 1926-2005, Bulk: 1940-1960
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Spanish Department
Inclusive: 1926-2005, Bulk: 1940-1960
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/155
Walker, Thomas F.
3 document boxes.
BU Records: Spanish Department consists of teaching materials, graded student output, correspondence, and promotional materials. Most, but not all, of these came from former professor Dr. Thomas F. Walker.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Dr. Thomas F. Walker received his master’s degree in Spanish from Baylor in 1946 after serving in the US Navy during World War II. He then went on to receive his PhD in Spanish from the University of Texas at Austin. After finishing his doctoral coursework, he returned to Baylor as a professor and stayed until his death in 1976. During his last ten years at Baylor, Dr. Walker served as the Spanish Department’s chairman. His publications include his master’s thesis, “The Historicity of the Chroniclers on the Conquest of Mexico,” and the chapter “The Struggle for Independence and the First Empire: Pre-Revolutionary Pamphleteering in Mexico” from Essays in Mexican History; The Charles Wilson Hackett Memorial Volume published by the Institute of Latin-American Studies at the University of Texas.
Baylor University’s Spanish Department is part of the Department of Modern Foreign Languages in the College of Arts and Sciences. The DMFL offers courses in eleven different modern languages, divided into four divisions: Asian and African Languages, French and Italian, German and Russian, and Spanish and Portuguese. The Spanish Department offers both an undergraduate and a graduate program. Highlights of the program include numerous study abroad opportunities and a chapter of Sigma Delta Pi, the National Collegiate Hispanic Honor Society.
Scope and Content
This collection begins in 1926 and ends in 2005, with some undated materials. The collection contains materials pertaining to the Spanish Department at Baylor University. The majority of these materials were obtained from former Spanish professor Dr. Thomas F. Walker after his retirement. The collection is divided into two series: T. F. Walker and Administrative.
Series I. T. F. Walker consists of materials from Walker’s time as a PhD student at The University of Texas at Austin, the bulk of which are between 1948 and 1950. The first two folders contain teaching materials, such as syllabi, handouts, blank exams, and instructions for the professors from the department. Folders 3-8 contain materials pertaining to Walker’s studies. These include notes, papers, and exams. Graded materials are restricted. The rest of the materials in Series I. derive from Walker’s time as a professor at Baylor, and range in date from 1950 to 1962. The first ten folders contain students’ term papers arranged by class. The last five folders contain Walker’s research materials and drafts of essays.
Series II. Administrative comprises of various materials pertaining to the department, but not belonging to Dr. Walker. This series has the widest date range, with the bulk of it coming from between 1930 and 1980. The first six folders contain student papers submitted to other professors in the department and are restricted. The remaining eight folders contain teaching materials, departmental correspondence, newspaper articles, and promotional materials for events, courses, and study abroad opportunities.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, the collection was arranged in three boxes. The first was labeled T. F. Walker, UT, the second was T. F. Walker, BU, and the third was Miscellaneous/Unknown. This arrangement has remained largely the same, with the exception of the identification of items in box three as departmental materials outside the scope of T. F. Walker.
Currently, the collection includes two series: I. T. F. Walker (with subseries of T. F. Walker, UT and T.F. Walker BU) and II. Spanish Department.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/155. Acquired 1977-09-29
Related Resources
Related references
University of Texas Institute of Latin-American Studies. “Essays in Mexican History; the Charles Wilson Hackett Memorial Volume.” Austin: The Institute of Latin American Studies, The University of Texas, 1958. [book]
Walker, Thomas F. “The Historicity of the Chroniclers on the Conquest of Mexico.” M.A. Thesis, Baylor University, 1946. [thesis]
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History -- 20th century.
Subjects
Baylor University -- Faculty.; College teachers -- Texas -- Waco.; Education -- Texas -- Waco.; Spanish language -- Study and teaching -- Texas.
Genres
Business correspondence.; Instructional and educational works.; Outlines and syllabi.; Promotional materials.
- T. F. Walker, 1940-1962, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The first eight folders contain teaching materials and doctoral student materials from T. J. Walker's time at the University of Texas. The teaching materials are arranged largely by date, but special care was taken to keep the student materials in roughly the same arrangement they were supplied in. The remaining folders in this series contain student term papers and materials from T. J. Walker's time at Baylor. These are separated into folders by class, and are arranged by date within the folders. The latter half of the series contains research materials and writing drafts which are kept largely in their original order.
  - Spanish 406-407, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Geography, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - PhD Materials (1 of 6), 1940-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - PhD Materials (2 of 6), 1940-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - PhD Materials (3 of 6), 1940-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - PhD Materials (4 of 6), 1940-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - PhD Materials (5 of 6), 1940-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - PhD Materials (6 of 6), 1940-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Spanish 203 Student Papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Spanish 208 Student Papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Spanish 211 Student Papers (1 of 2), 1950-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Spanish 211 Student Papers (2 of 2), 1950-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Spanish 225 Student Papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Spanish 370 Student Papers, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Spanish 373 Student Papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Spanish 374 Student Papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Student Papers (1 of 2), 1955-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Student Papers (2 of 2), 1955-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Writing and Research (1 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Writing and Research (2 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Writing and Research (3 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Writing and Research (4 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Writing and Research (5 of 5), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Administrative, 1926-2005, undated; 2
  This series contains various materials relating to Baylor's Spanish Department, including student papers, teaching materials, correspondence, and promotional materials. They are in good condition.
  - Spanish 101 Student Papers, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Spanish 221 Student Papers, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Spanish 203 Student Papers (1 of 2), 1935-1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Spanish 203 Student Papers (2 of 2), 1935-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Spanish 361 Student Papers (1 of 2), 1932 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Spanish 361 Student Papers (2 of 2), 1932 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Writing and Research (1 of 2), 1937, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Writing and Research (2 of 2), 1937, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Handouts, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Speech, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1947 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1948-1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Promotional Materials, 1926-2005 (Box 3, Folder 14)